翻译：CharlesChouBlues
转制请保留译者信息
这星球上的每个人
Every living person on this planet
都拥有独一无二的双眼
has their own unique pair of eyes,
每双眼睛自成一个宇宙
each their own universe.
我是伊恩·格雷博士
My name is Dr. Ian Gray.
我是一位父亲
I'm a father,
一位丈夫
a husband
也是一名科学家
and I'm a scientist.
当我还是孩子时就发现
When I was a child I realized that the camera
相机的原理与人眼相同
was designed exactly like the human eye,
光线从镜头中穿过
taking in light through a lens,
再被转化为图像
forming it into images.
我开始尽可能多地
I began taking as many pictures of eyes
用相机记录他人的双眼
as I possibly could.
我想为你们讲述一个故事
I'd like to tell you the story
有一双眼睛 改变了我的世界
of the eyes that changed my world.
请记住这双眼睛
Remember these eyes.
记住眼睛中的每一处细节
Remember all the details in these eyes.
好了
Okay.
在故事的开头 我还是一名26岁的博士在读生
It started when I was a 26-year-old PhD student
在纽约生活
living in New York.
那是八年前的万圣夜
It was Halloween,eight years ago.
你还好吧
You okay?
我在赏月
I'm watching the moon.
能给你的眼睛拍张照吗
Can I take a picture of your eyes?
为什么
Why?
个人爱好
It's just something I do.
好吧
Okay.
相机被我改良过了
I've perfected this.
嗨
Hi.
你知道雉的故事吗
Do you know the story of the Phasianidae?
不知道
No.
那是什么
What's that?
那是种鸟
It's a bird...
它能在眨眼间感受全部的时间
that experiences all of time in one instant.
它能同时歌唱爱和愤怒
And she sings the song of love and anger
恐惧与快乐
and fear and joy and sadness
还有悲伤
all at once...
所有的感情都会化作一种美妙的声音
all combined into one magnificent sound.
你是何方神圣
Where are you from?
外星人
Another planet.
那种鸟的声音是什么样的
What does the bird sound like?
就像这样
It sounds like this.
靠近点
Lean closer.
老天
Geez...
更像是噪音
It's more like noise.
是啊
Yeah.
当这种鸟
And this bird...
遇见它此生所爱的时候
when she meets the love of her life,
它会快乐 也会难过
is both happy and sad.
快乐是因为另一半的幸福才刚刚刚开始
Happy because she sees that,for him, it is the beginning,
难过是因为这幸福于它在眨眼间已然结束
and sad because she knows it is already over.
嘿 你想喝点什么吗
Hey, hey, do you want to get a drink?
不喝
I don't drink.
什么都不喝吗
Like, anything?
你明早醒来后不会后悔吧
You're not gonna regret this in the morning, right?
身份已确认
Your identity confirmed.
那个DNA转录因子项目 我做完了
I finished that transcription factor program.
昨晚做的？
Last night?
不是
No.
今早做的
This morning.
我干事可麻利了 小贱人
'Cause, bitch, I don't play.
这是录入基因  然后
Got the input genes, and then you put
你把转录因子... - 等等
your transcription factor... - Wait a minute.
你身上都是伏特加味
You stink of vodka.
我是说 这味道很难闻
I mean, like, bad. Like, it smells...
我知道 我知道我浑身酒臭味
Yeah, I know, I know I reek off vodka.
别那么大声说话
Stop talking so loud.
我把你全部的数据
Okay, I consolidated all your data
都整合进一个数据库了
into one database.
不用谢
You are welcome.
你太厉害了 我讨厌你
You're amazing.I hate you.
我爱你才帮你整理的
Well, I love you--that's why I do it.
对了
Oh, hey.
有个新的轮换学生给你带
You got a new rotating student.
一年级的
It's a first-year.
我了个...
Oh, sh...
好好当个保姆吧 伙计
Have fun babysitting, buddy.
你该嚼口香糖了
You need gum.
你该带孩子去了
You need to have fun babysitting.
凯伦 - 嗨 我是伊恩
Karen. - Hi. Ian.
稍等
Can I...?
跟我来
Follow me.
你正在尝试
You're attempting to make
让色盲老鼠分辨颜色？ - 最初的设想是这样
color-blind mice see color? - That's the idea.
不过在失败试验 编号...
But after failed experiment
352之后
352...
也许吧
we'll see.
为什么
Why?
什么为什么
Why what?
为什么这么多实验都失败吗
Do so many experiments fail?
为什么你想让色盲老鼠分辨颜色呢
Why are you interested in making color-blind mice see color?
为什么不呢
Why not?
你怎么确定它们能不能分辨颜色
How are you testing that they see color?
作为新来的实验室轮换助手
As the new rotating lab assistant,
你的工作就是
your job will be to do very boring,
做些无聊又重复的实验
very repetitive experiments,
说好听些还能算个笔记员
be a glorified note taker,
以及不要不停问我『为什么』
and not ask me "why" every five minutes.
好吗
Okay?
很好
Cool.
开始实验...
Commencing experiment...
编号353
3-5-3,
测试家养小鼠对光色素蛋白的反应
response to photopigment protein in Mus musculus.
对照组对象 B 贝塔的B
The control subjects B Beta
伽玛的G
G Gamma,
喜悦的E
E Euphoria,
P...
灵魂睡眠的P
Psychopannychia.
那词什么意思
I don't know what that means.
你可以查字典
Look it up.
感谢上帝的G
"G" as in goodness gracious,
拜托帮帮忙的H
"H" as in help me, please,
《祖兰德》的Z
"Z" as in Zoolander,
对照组对象为
are the mice muted
抑制光色素蛋白后的小鼠
with the photopigment protein.
当线条开始移动时
When we animate the lines...
色盲的小鼠
color-blind mice
会凝视前方
stare straight.
然后
Whereas...
祝我们好运吧
fingers crossed...
被抑制的小鼠
the muted mice..
视线会跟随线条移动
...track the lines with their eyes.
我的天 - 我的天啊
Holy shit. - Holy fucking shit.
这是在PAX6基因
Is this on the background
超表达的情况下发生的吗
of PAX6 overexpression?
你真是一年级生？
You're a first-year?
我知道了 你觉得一年级生什么都不懂
I know-- it's surprising I can put together a sentence.
抱歉 不过我之前那三个实验助手
Sorry, I... I asked my last three lab assistants
都让我直接给了学分送走了
not to come in and I'd sign their credits.
不管怎么说 这只是第一步
Anyway,this is just one step
后面还有很长很长的路要走
in a very, very long... process.
这只是个粗略的估计
This is a rough estimation,
人类的眼睛
but let's just say that the human eye
由12个重要部分组成
has 12 working parts, right?
而构造最简单的眼睛只含有一个部分
Simplest eye having one.
如果我们能通过单基因突变
So if we can fill in the gaps--
补全这之间的断层
the evolutionary gaps--
这之间的进化断层
using single mutations,
我们就可以描绘出
we can map out the most logical progression
构造最简单的眼睛
of the most basic eye...
向最复杂完备的人眼的演变过程
to the most complex, fully formed human eye.
我不明白 为什么要花时间做这件事
I don't understand--why take the time?
我们都知道眼睛是会进化的
We know that it evolved.
这只是个假设 还不是事实
It's an assumption;it's not a fact.
当你不再是一年级生的时候 你就会明白
When you're no longer a first-year, you'll see
事实的重要性
how important facts are.
好吧
Right.
这里的每一种动物
Each of these animals has an eye
都拥有最适应其生存环境的眼睛
that's best selected for its environment.
如果
It would be...
你能找到一个起源点的话
cleaner-- less variables--
就能排除更多不确定因素
if you had an origin.
继续
Go on.
你现在的起点是一
You start with one...
最后到达十二
to get to 12.
但如果存在零呢
But what if you had zero--
一个非视觉性组织
a non-seeing organism--
但拥有能演变为一只眼睛的基因构成
and built, genetically,an eye from scratch,
一个能演变成十二的零点
a zero to 12?
这个理论成立的证明 无懈可击
It'd be a perfect proof, unassailable.
非视觉性组织里不存在PAX6基因
Non-seeing organisms don't have the PAX6 gene.
你怎么知道 有人研究过所有的组织吗
How do you know? Has anyone ever checked all of them?
我不认为有人...
I don't think anyone has ever checked...
这么做过
all of them.
你之前就想到这点了
You've thought of this before?
那你为什么要惊讶
Why did you look surprised?
因为你也想到了
Because so have you.
好吧
Okay.
那群女孩是谁
Who were those girls?
哪群女孩？ - 万圣节派对上的
Which girls? - The ones at the Halloween party
都穿着SM行头
in the S&M outfits.
SM行头？
S&M outfits?
我遇到了其中一个女孩 但是不知道她的名字
I-I met one of them;I don't know her name.
我也没看见她的脸 但她的眼睛太美了
I don't know her face, but she had these most amazing eyes.
太特别了
So specific.
中心虹膜异色
Central heterochromia.
你提醒我了
Oh, reminds me.
猜我做了什么
Guess what I did.
什么
What?
我想到了
I figured out an improved
一种改良技术
implementation technique
来实践道格曼的生物测定学算法
for Daugman's biometrics algo.
你有没有过这种感觉 当你遇上某个
You ever feel like when you met someone,
填上了你心里一块空缺的人
they fill this hole inside of you,
在他们离开后
and then when they're gone...
你感觉身体变得空荡荡的
you feel that space painfully vacant?
你还好吧
Are you okay, man?
我很好啊
Yeah, yeah, I'm okay.
你还好吧
Are you okay?
你刚刚说什么 你刚才...
What did you just say? Did you just...
说话的方式 就像个诗人
The way you talked was,like, poetic.
太诡异了 - 你闭嘴
It was weird. - Shut the fuck up.
太诡异了 老兄 你居然也会...
So weird, dude, I can't believe...
糟了
Oh, shit.
这家伙的身体也空荡荡的
This guy is painfully vacant.
伊恩 瞧啊 他的身体也空...
Ian, look at him-- he's so painfully va...
他的身体也空荡荡了
He's so painfully vacant.
走开
Fuck off.
我要一包Verdict香烟
Can I get a pack of Verdict
再买一张威力球彩票
and a Powerball?
多少钱
How much is that?
十一块十一
$11.11.
十一
Eleven...
幸运十一号
Lucky elevens.
谢谢
Thanks.
凯伦
Karen.
你在做什么
What are you doing?
没有视觉的动物占物种总数的5%
Five percent of all animals don't have vision,
而世界上共有870万个物种
and there are 8.7 million species.
我把PAX6基因列导入数据库检索
So I blasted PAX6 at the database,
什么都没有发现
but nothing came up.
所以我开始手动测序DNA了
So I started sequencing by myself.
你测了多少种生物
How many did you sequence?
十二种 - 你已经测了十二种
12. - You've done 12.
那还剩下多少种呢
So how many do you have left?
大约四十二万六千种吧
Like, approximately 426,000.
你打算把那四十二万六千个名字
Are you going to write 426,000 names
都写在窗户上吗
on the window?
我会在窗户写满前找到结果的
I'm going to find it before I get to the end of the window.
好吧
Okay.
你在做什么
What are you doing?
我...什么都没做
I'm... I'm not doing anything.
我们可能永远也发现不了什么
You know we could be looking forever and find nothing.
寻找后一无所获也算一种发现
Turning over rocks and finding nothing is progress.
你现在能告诉我你从哪里来了么
太多地方了 不好说
So, are you gonna tell me where you're from?
So many places, I don't know.
哪些地方
Which places?
简单来说 我在阿根廷出生
To make it short,I was born in Argentina,
11岁那年 我跟祖母一起搬到了法国
and when I was 11, I moved to France with my grandmother.
你的父母呢
And your parents?
下一个问题
Next.
你做什么工作
So, what do you do?
下一个问题
Next.
你那天为什么要和我上床
Why did you sleep with me that night?
判断失误
Poor judgment.
我寂寞了很久
I was lonely for a long time, and...
那天晚上我看到你时
...when I saw you that night,
感觉我们似曾相识
I had the feeling that I had known you.
事实上 我觉得你认识我
Actually, I felt like you knew me.
什么意思
What do you mean?
就像我们前世有过交集
Like we are connected from past lives.
我不相信这个
I don't believe in that.
那你相信什么
What do you believe in?
我是科学家 我相信数据
I'm a scientist;I believe in data.
科学家
A scientist?
哪种科学家
What kind of scientist?
分子生物学
Molecular biology.
我对眼睛最感兴趣
I'm most fascinated with the eye.
眼睛 这种眼睛吗
The eye...the eyes?
就是眼睛 - 为什么是眼睛
The eyes. - Why the eye?
眼睛
The eye is
是信仰宗教的人
the one sticking point that religious people use
拒绝承认进化论的根据
to discredit evolution.
他们把眼睛看作智慧的造物者存在的证明
They use it as proof of a intelligent designer.
造物者？
Intelligent designer?
就是上帝
God.
我打算用清晰 彻底的事实
I'm looking to end the debate once and for all with...
来终结这场争论
...clear, clean facts.
也就是眼睛每个进化阶段的数据
Data points of every stage of eye evolution.
你为什么要努力去证明上帝是不存在的呢
Why are you working so hard to disprove God?
证明？又有谁证明过上帝是存在的吗？
Disprove? Who proved that God was there in the first place?
总之 我想先拿到
Anyway,let's get some real
关于你的数据 可以吗
data points on you, okay?
请便
Be my guest.
我也更喜欢说关于自己的事
I prefer talking about myself anyways.
好吧
Okay.
你最喜欢的...
Um, what's your favorite,
糖果？
Candy?
草莓曼妥斯
Strawberry Mentos.
喜欢的食物？
Food?
蔬菜玉米卷
Veggie burritos.
先说一声 我是素食主义者
I'm vegetarian,you should know that.
你最喜欢哪种花
What's your favorite flower?
蒲公英
Dandelions.
为什么
Okay. Why?
因为它们在野外自由生长
'Cause, they're free, wild,
不会被放在花店里出售
and you can't buy them.
你喜欢哪门学科？
What's your favorite field of study?
星象学
The stars.
最喜欢的动物
What's your favorite animal?
白孔雀
The white peacock.
你见过白孔雀吗
You ever see one?
没有
No.
纽约有一只
There's one in New York.
我带你去看
I'll take you to see it.
所以我们还会见面？
So, you're gonna see me again?
也许吧
Maybe.
在印度神话中
You know,in Indian mythology,
白孔雀象征着
the white peacock symbolizes
散落在世上的灵魂
souls being dispersed throughout the world.
你有没想过 它可能只意味着
Did you ever think it just symbolizes
细胞中缺乏色素的孔雀
a lack of melanin or pigment in the cells?
对照组对象 T
The control subjects "T..."
海啸的T
"T" as in tsunami.
G是...
"G" as in...
矮人的G
Gnome.
P是...
"P" as in...
肺炎的P
Pneumonia.
M是...
"M" as in...
记忆的M
Mnemonic.
我看见了很多个11 到处都是
I start to see these elevens,like, everywhere.
太多11了
Too many elevens.
数量多到难以置信
The amount was so staggering, so unlikely,
于是我就沿着数字向前走
that I followed them.
数字带我找到了你的眼睛
And when I followed them,I found your eyes,
然后带我找到了你
which then led me to you.
我通过你的眼睛找到了你
Because I found you through your eyes.
难以置信
Also unlikely...
像生命本身一样神奇
like life itself.
我知道
I know.
我向你发出的讯号
I sent them to you.
怎么可能
Bullshit.
你明白的
You know you have it.
明白什么 - 但是你害怕它
Have what? - But you're scared of it.
什么东西
I have what?
好吧
Okay.
你住在这个房间里 对吧
You live in this room, right?
这房间代表现实
Reality.
你有一张床 你有书
You have a bed, you have books,
还有一张桌子 椅子 台灯
um, a desk, a chair, lamps.
逻辑
Logic.
但这房间
But in this room,
同时也有一扇门
you have a door...
通往另一侧
to the other side.
看到没
See?
光可以照进来
Light comes through.
门是开着的
It's open
虽然只是很窄一条缝 但门是开着的
just a tiny bit,but it is open.
你因为害怕所以一直试图关上那扇门
You keep trying to close that door because you're scared.
但你不会永远害怕
But you won't always be scared.
门后面有什么
What's behind the door?
除了我的脏衣服之外
Besides my dirty laundry.
你要走到另一边才能知道
You have to go in to find out.
你明白我的意思
You know what I'm talking about.
我不明白
I have no idea.
你会明白的
You will.
你会的
想要搬到我那里住吗
You want to move to my place?
你也有住的地方？
You have a place?
当然了
Of course.
明天就搬可以吗
Can I move in tomorrow?
这是你家人吗
Is this your family?
嗯 这是我的祖母
Yes, it's my grandmother.
她有种奇特的美
Such an eccentric beauty.
然后
And...
这是我父母和小时候的我
...my parents and me when I was a baby.
白孔雀
Um, the white peacock.
你已经见过了
But you have met him before.
这是灵魂存在的证明
This is a proof of the spirit world.
『重生天使』
"El Ángel de la Resurreccion."
什么
What?
这座雕像的名字
It's the name of the statue,of the statue
圣安妮公墓的一尊雕像
in St. Anne's Cemetery.
圣安妮公墓里的雕像？
It's in St. Anne's Cemetery?
看他的眼睛
But look at the eyes.
这双眼睛是有生命的
They're alive.
是啊
Yeah.
现在什么照片都能用电脑做出来
It's amazing what you can do on Photoshop these days.
这不是电脑做的
There's no Photoshop!
眼睛是在她拍下照片时浮现出来的
The eyes appeared just when she took the picture.
就在...
Just...
你真美
You're so beautiful.
去把盒子搬进来
Let's get more boxes.
妊娠期第19天
19 days gestation period.
实验对象就绪
She is ready.
名誉 研究经费
Fame, science grants,
还有财富 都在未来等着你
fortune await you.
如果你找到PAX6基因
If you find that PAX6 gene,
那些东西离我们也不远了
we'll be well on our way to all of that.
知名度这种事让我觉得恶心
Recognition makes me extremely nauseous.
但让人们了解研究成果是很重要的
Well, it is important that people know about the work.
对我来说 做实验室里的小白鼠 最好的一点...
To me, the best thing about living like a lab rat...
就是有时候...
is that sometimes...
在屈指可数的几个时刻
really rare times,
当你真的发现了什么的时候
you actually discover something.
带着新发现的喜悦躺在床上的那个夜晚
On the night of a discovery,when you're lying in bed,
你就是世界上唯一掌握着全新真理的人
you are the only person in the world that knows it's true.
能答应我一件事吗
Can you promise me something?
答应你什么
Promise you something?
什么
What?
答应我
Promise.
你得先告诉我是什么事 我才能...
I can't promise if you don't tell me what...
先答应我
Promise first.
在你告诉我是什么事之前？
Before you tell me what it is?
我是守信的人
I keep my promises.
不管 不答应就不说
Whatever, I won't tell.
答应我
Promise.
好吧 我答应你
Okay, I promise.
我希望你把我烧掉
I want you to burn me.
烧掉？
Burn you?
我不想死后烂在一个箱子里
I don't want to rot in a box when I die.
噢 你是说 火化你
Oh, you mean like cremate you.
对
yeah.
不行 不行
Oh, no, no.
我不想被火化
I don't want to be cremated.
我都不知道我们还有这种分歧
This is a big disagreement I didn't know we had.
火化相当于彻底抹消了存在
Cremation is like obliteration.
我是说 如果在未来 科学家们...
I mean, what if in the future,the scientists...
发现了通过DNA构造一个新的我们的方法怎么办
what if they can reconstitute ourselves through our DNA?
我要和你说清楚
I want to be clear with you.
我不想那样
I don't want that.
你不想做什么
You don't want what?
我不想被克伦
I don't want to be cloning.
克隆 克...
"Cl-Cloneed." Cl...
『我不想被克伦』
"I don't want to be cloning."
克隆
"Cloneed."
我会先重组一个自己
No, but I'd reconstitute myself first,
然后再重组你 接着我会问你
and then I'd reconstitute you,and then I'd ask you,
『你想活下去吗』
"Do you want to be alive?"
如果你不想的话 我再把你杀了
And then if you didn't,I'd kill you.
开玩笑的 我们到时候可以永远在一起了
No, but then we could be together forever, like, like,
从科学角度说 我们真的可以被... - 你不能...
for real, scientifically. - You can't do...
被复活 被重组
Reanimated, reconstituted.
你是个放不下过去的人
You have a hard time letting go.
别担心
Don't worry.
我们会再次找到对方的
We'll find each other again.
我喜欢你的香水
I love your smell.
是什么
What is it?
不告诉你
I won't tell.
告诉我吧
Come on, tell me.
嫁给我好吗
Will you marry me?
下一位
Next?
请问要办理什么
Can I help you?
我们要结婚
We'd like to get married.
你们身份证带了吗
Do you have your I.D.'s?
带了
Yeah.
可以了 首先你们需要领取结婚证
Okay, first you have to get your marriage license,
这些表格需要你们填写
so you have to fill these out.
好的
Okay.
你们需要等待24小时
You're gonna have to wait 24 hours
才能成为合法夫妻
before you can actually get married.
24小时
24 hours?!
是的 - 为什么
Yeah. - Why?
这样一来 你就有24小时
Well, this way,you have 24 hours
决定你是否真的想嫁给这位年轻人
to decide whether you want to marry this young man.
我想嫁给他啊
But I want to marry him!
24小时后才行
In 24 hours.
所以...好吧 我知道了
So... Okay. All right. Yeah.
我们不能今天结婚了
So we can't get married today.
好吧
Okay...
这个规定确实...
This system really...
有点儿泼冷水的感觉 是吧
kills the spontaneity factor, huh?
没关系 我们精神上在一起了
We're already married in the spirit world.
该死
Shit.
喂
Hello?
嗨
Hi.
怎么了 你打了我五通电话了
Hi. What's up? You called, like, five times.
是啊
I did.
我为什么会打那么多次呢
Why would I do that?
我为什么会打五次呢
Why might I call five times?
我不知道
I don't know.
我今天在做电泳测试
I was running the electrophoretic drill--
就是周二的日常
you know,just another Tuesday--
然后我开始给一种
and I started sequencing the genes
叫赤子爱胜蚓的奇怪虫子做基因测序
of this strange worm called Eisenia fetida.
继续
Go on.
然后
And, uh...
我发现了PAX6的总开关基因
I found the PAX6 master switch.
不可能
No.
是真的 - 你是认真的吗
Yeah. - Are you serious right now?
你没开玩笑吧 你知道这意味着什么吗
You fucking with me? Do you know what this means?
我们发现了原初物种
We found an origin species,
我们可以创造出眼睛了
and we can build an eye from scratch.
我的天...！
Holy sh...!
那个...它有没有..
Um, uh, does it...does it have
和人类相同的氨基酸序列
the same amino acid sequence as humans?
我现在...
I-I can't even...
我现在已经说不出话了
I can't even talk right now.
我觉得我快失禁了
I feel like I'm gonna piss myself.
你能直接过来吗
Can you just come in here?
好的 我马上过去
Okay, I'm coming in right now.
你太棒了
You're amazing.
再见 先挂了
Bye. Bye-bye. Bye.
谁的电话
Who was that?
是凯伦...
That was Karen, uh...
我的轮换...
my rotating...
我的实验伙伴
well... my lab partner.
我现在得去实验室一趟
I have to go into the lab, right now.
你要和我一起来吗 - 今天不是我们结婚的日子吗
Do you want to come with me? - On our wedding day?
今天...不是
It's... well, it's not...
严格来说 今天不是我们结婚的日子
technically,it's not our wedding day today.
而且我们的灵魂
And we've been married forever
不是已经永远结合了吗
in the spiritual world, right?
苏菲 求你了 跟我一起去吧
Sofi, please,come in with me.
这真的很重要
It's really important.
好吧
Sure.
不要紧的 我们走吧
It's fine. Let's go.
别难过了
Well,don'be upset about it.
我们把戒指戴上吧
Let's put our rings on.
不要 这会走霉运的
I don't want to;it's bad luck.
我不相信运气
I don't believe in luck.
不过我相信 我们从很久很久以前
I do believe we've known each other
就已经认识彼此了
since forever, though.
真的吗
Really?
是啊 知道为什么吗
Yeah.You know how?
当宇宙大爆炸发生的时候
When the big bang happened,
宇宙中的所有原子都碰撞在一起
all the atoms in the universe,they were all smashed together
变成一个小点 然后从里面迸发开来
into one little dot that exploded outward.
所以我的原子和你的原子 在那时候一定是靠在一起的
So my atoms and your atoms were certainly together then,
然后 也许...
and, who knows, probably...
在过去的13.7亿年中
smashed together several times in the last 13.7
也碰撞过几次
billion years.
所以的原子认识你的原子
So my atoms have known your atoms...
它们长久以来都认识你的原子
and they've always known your atoms.
我的原子一直爱着你的原子
My atoms have always loved your atoms.
走吧
Let's go.
凯伦
Karen.
嘿 - 嗨
Hey. - Hi.
嗨 这位是...苏菲 这是凯伦
Hi. This is...Sofi, this is Karen.
凯伦 这是苏菲 - 嗨
Karen, this is Sofi. - Hi.
她是我妻子
She's my wife.
欢迎
Welcome. Um...
你想看什么
What do you want to see?
所有的东西
I want to see everything.
我现在得到了这样的胶体
So, I have this gel.
是一致的吗
And it aligns?
和PAX6蛋白的交叉比对结果
The alignment crossed PAX6 proteins...
重合度98%
98% identity.
这就是那种虫子吗
Are these the worms?
它们还什么都看不见呢
They can't see anything.
很快就可以了
Not for long.
我...
You know, um...
我想先回去洗个澡
I should... I'm gonna go take a shower.
你也已经看过了
You've seen it.
我得去洗个澡 - 洗澡？
I should take a shower - Shower?
再刷个牙 - 等一下 你这就走了？
brush my teeth... - Wait a minute,you're gonna go right now
嗯
yeah.
是啊 我觉得你可以带你妻子参观下实验室
Yeah, I'm sure you want to show your wife around the lab and...
好的 你确定吗
Okay. Are you sure?
好吧 那么...
Okay. Well, uh...
你做得很棒
this is amazing.
大发现的开始
The beginning of something...
棒极了
amazing.
很高兴认识你
It was nice to meet you.
你太棒了 凯伦
Amazing stuff, Karen.
拜 - 拜
Bye. - Bye.
拜
Bye.
怎么了
What's wrong?
我知道你不高兴了
I know something's wrong, so...
你每天离开我到这里折磨这些小虫子？
You leave me every day to torture little worms?
我们没有折磨它们 苏菲
We're not torturing worms... Sofi.
如果你想知道的话
If you're interested,
我们在改造生物
we're modifying organisms.
在这个实验中 对象碰巧是虫子
In this case,they happen to be worms,
它们看不见东西
that are blind,
我们正试图赋予它们视力
and we're modifying them to have vision.
你可以让没有视力的虫子看见东西？
You can make blind worms see?
差不多吧
Kind of.
我是说 现在我们应该有这个能力了
I mean, we can now, maybe.
你觉得这是个好主意吗
You think that's a good idea?
你觉得这是个坏主意吗
Do you think it's a bad idea?
我觉得
I think...
以上帝自居是要付出代价的
it's dangerous to play God.
苏菲 我相信的是实证
Sofi, I believe in proof.
没有证据可以表明
There is no proof
世间存在某种
that there is some magical spirit...
不可见的 凌驾于我们之上的
uh, that's invisible,living above us,
神灵之力
right on top of us...
这些小虫有多少种感觉
How many senses do worms have?
两种
They have two:
嗅觉
smell...
和触觉
and touch.
为什么问这个
Why?
那么...
So...
它们一直在没有视觉的情况下生活着
they live without any ability to see
更不知道光的存在 对吗
or even know about light, right?
光线的概念之于它们
The notion of light to them is...
是不可想象的
unimaginable.
是的
Yeah.
但是
But...
我们人类
we humans...
我们知道
we know...
光是存在的
that light exists...
它们的四周有光
all around them,
它们头顶上也有光
right on top of them.
它们感觉不到光 但
They cannot sense it, but...
经过一些小小的变异 它们就能看见光了
with a little mutation, they do.
是吗
Right?
没错
Correct.
所以...
So...
眼睛博士
Dr. Eye...
也许某些人类
perhaps some humans--
极少数人类
rare humans--
也发生了变异 得到了一种全新的感觉
have mutated to have another sense--
他们能感觉灵魂的存在
a spirit sense--
他们能看见
and can perceive a world
我们头顶上存在的另一个世界
that is right on top of us...
无处不在的另一个世界
everywhere...
就像光线之于这些小虫一样
just... like the light on these worms.
那么 你是变种人咯
So you're a mutant.
不止我一个
And I'm not the only one.
老天 - 你没事吧 我看看
- Jesus! - Are you okay? Here, let me see.
福尔马林进到我眼睛里了 拿冲洗设备来
I got formaldehyde in my eye. Get the splash kit.
- 那是什么 - 该死的！
- What is it? - Aah! Fuck!
那是什么 告诉我 - 是黄色的
What is it? Tell me! - It's-it's... yellow!
就在那儿
It's right over there.
黄色的 打电话给凯伦 快点打电话给凯伦
It's yellow. Call Karen. Fucking call Karen now.
号码是多少！ - 就写在门边上
Where's the number! - The number's by the door.
门边上
By the door.
找到了
Got it.
我们每周五都该演练下这种情况
We should do this every Friday.
看一下这是几
How many fingers am I holding up?
12 - 他没瞎
12. - He's not blind.
这是个好消息
So that's good.
我觉得你不要紧了
I think you're gonna be fine.
你还好吧
Are you okay?
还好
Yeah.
好了
Okay.
谢谢你 - 没事
- Thank you. - Yeah.
差不多过...
You're gonna feel fine in...
12小时左右就好了
12 hours or something.
我明天再打电话问下情况
I'll call tomorrow and check in on him.
谢谢 - 不客气
Thank you. - Yeah, of course.
真有趣
This is funny.
嗯 我觉得...
Yeah. It's, um...
有点奇怪
...strange.
猜我在哪
Find me.
诶呀
Whoa.
怎么了
Whoa what?
我们停在两层楼中间了
We are in the middle of two floors.
电梯卡住了
We stopped.
我们该给楼管打电话
We should call the super.
什么楼管
The super what?
楼管 大楼管理员
The super. The superintendent. Um,
负责检修楼房的人
the guy that fixes the building.
你能给他打个电话吗
Can you call him?
我不认识这个人 我没有他的号码
I don't know this guy.I don't have his number.
我都忘了这回事
Of course you don't.
拿着
Here.
通讯录里的那个『楼管』
It's under "super."
怎么了
What?
你手机没电了
Your phone is dead.
没电了？ - 是啊
It's dead? - Yeah.
别这样 放轻松
Now, come on, relax.
你真是靠不住
You're so irresponsible.
哦
Okay...
要我给凯伦打电话吗
Want me to call Karen?
别耍小孩子脾气
Don't be a child.
你一直活在童话 魔法
You live in this fairy, magical...
幻想的世界里
fantasy land.
那些都他妈是骗人的 你知道那是骗人的
It's a fucking lie,and you know it's a lie.
你总是...
That's...
你总是想要去相信这种谎话 就像个孩子一样
it's a lie that you want to believe, like a child.
像个孩子一样
Like a child.
好了 好了
Okay. Okay.
过来
Come on.
我们该怎么办 - 我把你推上去
What's gonna happen? - I'll boost you up.
00:44:37,909 - -> 00:44:39,842
我不要 你先上去 - 来吧
No, no, no, you go first - Come on.
然后再拉我上去 - 苏菲 别这样
and you pull me up. - Sofi, come on...
我不要先上去 你先上去
I'm not going first. You go first.
瞧你 怕成这个样子 快来
Look at you. You're so scared. Come on.
当心
Be careful.
你看 很容易就上来了吧
Look how easy that was.
来吧
Come on.
来吧 上来
Come on, let's go.
上来啊 苏菲雅
Sofia, come on!
抓住我的手
Give me your hand.
好了 来吧
Okay, come on.
苏菲？
Sofi?
苏菲？苏菲？
Sofi? Sofi?
苏菲 苏菲？
苏菲？
Sofi?
苏菲！
Sofi!
喂
Hello?
我可以过去吗
Can I come over?
不行
No.
大概吧
Maybe.
如果说我这里有一样
What if I bring you something
会让你大吃一惊的东西呢
that I know will take your breath away.
它有眼睛了
It has an eye.
虽然还是简单的感光细胞 不过...
I mean, just light-sensitive cells, but...
我们做到了
we did it.
变异保留了下来
Mutations are holding.
是你做到的
You did it.
这只是一小步 前面的路还很长
That's the first step in a really long process.
如果你不能打起精神回到实验室工作
It's gonna end as a worm in a box
这项发现可能会止步于盒子里的一只小虫
if you don't get your ass back in the lab.
吃点东西吧
Why don't you eat something.
他声称已经找到了
He claims to have put to rest the notion
能让人们相信眼睛并非上帝造物的证据
that the eye was made by an intelligent designer.
格雷博士 你认为单凭实验室中创造的几个变异体
Dr. Gray, you made some mutants in a laboratory,
就足以让信仰宗教的人们
and now you expect all religious people
摒弃自己的信仰吗
to what, just throw away their beliefs?
我认为他们会
Well, I expect them to fight me
反对我提出的每一个观点
every step of the way.
但我恳切地希望
But I do implore them to look
他们能够看看我们迄今为止收集的数据与证明
at the evidence and data that we've collected here.
这些样本充分说明了
These specimens are practical examples
眼睛每个阶段的演化过程
of every stage of eye development.
很高兴您今天能来 伊恩·格雷博士
Dr. Ian Gray,thanks for being here.
谢谢你们的邀请
Thanks for having me.
这本书的名字是《完全之眼》
Uh, the book is The Complete Eye.
好了
All right.
我表现如何
How'd I do?
你干嘛做出那个表情
Why do you do that thing with your face?
你说什...
What-what do you...?
你刚才就像这样 这样
That thing where you're,like...
你表情很正常 - 表现很好 很好
You did nothing with your face. - It was good,it was good.
我觉得你应该
Man, you should have joined
去私企工作 教授先生
the private sector, Professor.
太疯狂了 虹膜识别技术
It's crazy.Iris biometrics is...
已经在世界各地流行开来了
exploding all over the world.
我可是把爱人放在第一位的
I'll take love over money any day.
你还真成熟呢
Wow, that's mature of you.
你觉得他们会聘用我吗
You think I could really get a job there?
谢谢
Thank you.
怎么了
You all right?
还需要酒水吗
Any more drinks?
没事 我只是...
Uh, yeah, I just...
闻到了似曾相识的味道
there's a smell,I can't place it.
可能是你的香水
Maybe it's your perfume.
还需要酒水吗
Any more drinks?
不用了 我们想知道
Uh, no, actually,we'd like to know
你香水的牌子 - 不用回答这个问题
what your perfume is? - You don't have to answer that.
兰蔻璀璨
It's Tresor.
璀璨？
Tresor?
很好闻 - 谢谢
It's lovely. - Thank you.
我不介意再来一杯
I'm okay with drink.
璀璨
It's Tresor.
这是法语词
It's French.
你该不会...
Are you hitting on the...
当着怀孕老婆的面勾搭女服务生吧
waitress in front of your pregnant wife?
我确定你是不是了解我 肯尼
I don't know if you know this about me, Kenny,
我负责嫉妒的基因是 隐性的
but the gene for jealousy--recessive.
那挺好的 对他来说
That's... that's good, for him.
我要带着我漂亮的 怀孕的老婆去跳舞了
I'm going to the dance floor with my pregnant, lovely wife.
我待会帮你问她的号码
I'm gonna get her number for you.
失陪啦
Please. Thank you.
我已经等不及
I'm so looking forward
要和你一起给宝宝洗脑了
to brainwashing this child with you.
你知道我怎么想吗
You know what I was thinking?
什么
What?
如果我们把车库改造成实验室
What if we turn the garage into a lab?
然后拿宝宝当我们的第一个实验对象
And the baby could be our first test subject.
真是个好主意
That's a great idea.
从道德上讲有不对的地方吗
Is there something ethically wrong with that?
没有
No.
你知道我在想什么吗
You know what I want to do?
我们该离开这里
I think we should leave.
我来帮我妻子
I'm, uh, picking up a prescription
凯伦·格雷 取药
for my wife, Karen Gray.
妈妈唱首歌给你听吧
How about if I sing to you?
美丽的梦中人
Beautiful dreamer
请为我醒来
Wake unto me...
白日的喧嚣
Sounds of the rude world
已经过去
Heard in the day
银色的月光
Lull'd by the moonlight
散发光彩
Have all pass'd away...
美丽的梦中人
Beautiful dreamer
请为我醒来
Wake unto me
星光和露珠
Starlight and dewdrops
正为你等待
Are waiting for thee
看镜头 说你好
Say hello to the camera.
苏菲 快点
Sofi, come on.
温柔点
Be nice.
温柔点 像个淑女那样
Be nice. Come on, act like a lady.
你好 - 你好
Hello.- Hello.
你好 - 我想要你
Hello. - I want you.
我更想要你
I want you more.
别停下来
Don't stop.
我想看看什么东西让你这么兴奋
I want to know what's turning you on.
我之前从没这样过
I never do this.
有时我会思考那件事的前因后果是什么
I sometimes think about the cause and effect of it,
我想 —— 我并没有觉得内疚
and I think about how-- and I don't feel guilty for this...
但是我会想
...but I think about how
如果我那天没有打电话叫你去实验室
if I hadn't called you into the lab that day...
她可能不会...她可能还会活着
she would...maybe still be here,
而你还和她在一起
and you would be with her.
跟你说一件让我觉得自己很残忍的事
Can I tell you something that makes me feel like a monster?
那天 在电梯里
That day in the elevator,
我想 『我是不是这辈子』
I thought,"Am I going to be stuck
『都要和这个长不大的孩子困在这里了』
with this child the rest of my life?"
然后下一秒 她就死了
And then the next moment, she was dead.
我们不可能在一起的 凯伦
We were never gonna be...together, Karen.
我只是一直没有...
I just never got...
解脱出来
closure.
我一直没机会...
I never got to say...
和她告别
good-bye.
吻我
Kiss me.
虹膜扫描技术是现在许多大医院
Iris scanning is a new identification measure taken up
都开始采用的新型身份识别技术
by the more sophisticated hospitals.
我们知道什么是虹膜扫描
We know what iris scanning is.
我们的实验室已经用了有十年了
We've had it in our lab for a... for a decade.
这对于大众来说还是项新技术
Well, it's still new to the general public.
虽然现在法律还没有规定
Now, we are not yet legally required
要做虹膜扫描登记 不过我们已经启用了机器
to scan eyes, but we adopted the technology
只要父母同意就可以给孩子扫描
and use it with the parents' consent.
我不介意 你觉得呢
I'm fine with it. Do you, uh...?
我也不介意 扫描吧 - 我先把灯关掉
Scan, yeah. Do the scan.  - I dim the lights.
扫描不会造成伤害
The system is non-obtrusive,
事实上
and in all actuality
就是给眼睛拍照而已
is just taking photo of the eyes.
开始咯 - 躺好 托比亚斯
There you go. - Come here, Tobias.
谢谢 - 可以了吗
Oh, thank you. - You got it?
可以了 谢谢
Yes, I got it. Thank you.
接下来 电脑会处理图像
What happens then is,the computer finds
在眼睛的缝隙中找出许多定点
a bunch of points in the crevices of the eye...
我们知道这个原理的
Yeah, we-we understand how it works.
噢 抱歉
Oh, forgive me.
这是新系统 能看出来吧
These systems are sort of new.Can you tell?
保罗·埃德加·戴瑞？
Paul Edgar Dairy?
像海盗的名字
Sounds like a pirate.
出现这种情况的时候 我就得输入操作码
If this happens,I'm supposed to punch in a key
然后重启
and reboot.
稍等
Wait.
好了
There we go.
现在我要录入他的身份信息
So I'll just put in his info.
宝宝叫什么名字
What is his name?
我觉得叫保罗·埃德加·戴瑞也挺好
I like Paul Edgar Dairy.It's fine.
托比亚斯·乔治·格雷
Tobias George Gray.
和他祖父的名字一样
After his grandfather.
喂？ - 你好 是伊恩·格雷吗
Hello? - Hi. Is this Ian Gray?
是的 - 我是西蒙斯博士
It is. - My name is Dr. Simmons.
我是耶鲁大学和格林威治医院合作机构的
I work in conjunction with Yale and the Greenwich hospital
您妻子七月份是在那里生产的对吧
where you and your wife gave birth in July.
是的 有什么问题吗
Yeah, yeah.Is everything okay?
没什么问题 请不要紧张
Yes, everything's okay.Please don't be alarmed.
不过 我们有几项简单的测试
We would, however,like to run
想要让托比亚斯参与
a few simple tests on Tobias.
他的检查结果显示...虽然这概率非常小
His test results may suggest, although highly unlikely,
但他有患上早期自闭症的风险
the possibility of early autism.
我也是内行人 什么测试
You know I'm a doctor. What test results?
我们确定了...
We've pinpointed...
麻烦稍等一下
Can you hold on a moment, please?
凯伦 听电话
Karen, listen to this.
请讲
Yeah.
我们已经确定了一系列
We've pinpointed an array of molecular compounds
自闭症患儿尿液中
that appear in the urine
会包含的分子化合物
of children with autism...
而托比亚斯的样本包含了
and Tobias showcased
部分此类化合物 但我保证他患病的几率很小
a few of them.I promise it's unlikely,
但还是应该检查一下 过程很简单
but worth checking out,and we have very simple,
不会造成任何伤害 大概一小时内就能完成
non-obtrusive tests,and we'll be done in an hour.
请问您的名字和所属机构是？
What was your name and affiliation?
詹妮特·西蒙斯博士
Dr. Janet Simmons.
我与耶鲁大学和格林威治医院
I run a research lab on child autism
合作运营一所儿童自闭症研究实验室
in conjunction with Yale and the Greenwich hospital.
西蒙斯对吧 - 詹妮特·西蒙斯
Simmons, you said? - Janet Simmons.
我们的诊所离斯坦福德市不远
Our clinic is in Stamford,not too far from there.
我建议还是尽早检查比较好
It's important to check this soon.
你们...
There's...
不用太急 但今天内能来最好
no alarming rush, but we could see him today.
好的 谢谢 我们再联系
Okay. Thank you.You'll hear from us.
托比亚斯
Tobias.
看这里 看这里
Look here. Look here.
我不太明白
I'm not sure I understand
这个测试和自闭症有什么关系
how this is testing for autism.
血检和尿检可以检测出分子化合物
The blood and urine tests will check for molecular compounds.
而通过这项感知能力测试
This test is purely perceptual,
我们追踪孩子的眼部运动
tracking the child's eye movements
看他们会被什么所吸引
and attractions.
行了 可以了 - 好了 测试结束了
Okay, that's enough. - Yeah. The test is over.
如果您来电查询
If you are calling regarding
现存的孩童资料
an existing child,
请输入对应的七位数查询编码
please enter your seven-digit session number.
这个西蒙斯博士在研究某种东西
This Dr. Simmons is up to something.
儿童自闭症 鬼才相信
Child autism, my ass.
我一直在观察她的测试
I keep running through her studies.
两张并排的图片 她到底在研究什么
What was she doing? Two images side by side.
两张图片 相似但又有区别
Two images,similar but different.
托比亚斯会望向其中的一张
Tobias would look at one or the other.
你还记得那些图片的细节吗
Do you remember anything specific about the images?
能看出什么联系吗
Something connected to something?
有什么可以查到的吗
Something we could look up?
我记得有一个...农场
There was a...farmhouse.
还有...
There was, um...
爱达荷州博伊西的丹氏餐车
Dan's Diner in Boise, Idaho.
不知道什么意思
Whatever that means.
真有这么个地方
Well, that's a real place.
你好
Hello.
要点些什么
What can I get you?
一杯咖啡就好
Um, just a cup of coffee.
没问题
Sure thing.
我是外地来的
I'm not from around here.
我想问问 这里有没有什么地方
I was wondering, is there anything interesting
值得参观的
in town to see?
这块儿没什么好看的
Not much around these parts.
除非你对奶牛有兴趣
Unless you,fancy visiting some cows
附近有个奶牛农场
down at the dairy farm.
奶牛农场？
There's a dairy farm?
总共一美元
That'll be a dollar.
好的
Of course.
那个奶牛农场在什么地方
Where is the dairy farm located?
这儿左转 开个两英里左右就能看见了
Uh, take a left,about two miles down the road.
很好找的
Can't miss it.
稍等一会就好
We'll have 'em through in a moment.
好的
Okay.
快点
Come on!
这里是奶牛场吗
Is this the dairy farm?
是的
Indeed it is.
这些是奶牛吗
These are milking cows?
这些是肉牛 不是奶牛
These are meat cows,not milking cows.
我是茱丽·戴瑞
I'm Julie Dairy.
这是我们家的农场
This is my family's farm.
茱丽·戴瑞
Julie Dairy?
保罗·埃德加·戴瑞
Uh, Paul Edgar Dairy.
是你的家人吗
Are you related to him?
对 他是我父亲
Yes, he's my father.
他在吗
Is he here?
所以你不是和做人物采访的那些人一起的
You're clearly not with the biography association.
不好意思
The, um, I'm sorry.
我没听明白
I don't follow.
几个月前有一群拍纪录片的人来这儿
Some documentary crew came through here a few months ago,
说是要做一期保罗·埃德加·戴瑞的故事
wanting to do a story on the great Paul Edgar Dairy,
博伊西唯一的黑人农场主
the only black farmer in Boise.
他们拍了些照片
They took some pictures.
我喜欢这个故事 然后他们说还会再来的
I liked the story, and they said they'd follow up.
你没事吧？
You okay?
你好啊
How you doing there?
我没事
I'm okay.
我只是突然有种...
I'm just, uh, having a moment
即视感
of déjà vu.
要喝点水吗
Can we fetch you some water?
或者茶
Or a cup of tea?
如果可能的话 我想见见保罗
I'd really love to meet Paul,if that was possible.
不如我们回到最开始 一步步来看
What if we just start at the beginning and break it down?
先是在医院里 托比亚斯的眼部扫描
In the hospital,Tobias's eyes come up as a match
和保罗·埃德加·戴瑞的结果匹配 但明显是不对的
with Paul Edgar Dairy,which is not correct,
托比亚斯的眼睛是蓝色
because Tobias has blue eyes
保罗·埃德加·戴瑞的是褐色
and Paul Edgar Dairy has brown eyes.
不是这样的 虹膜识别技术不以眼睛颜色做区分
Uh, no, iris biometrics is not based on color.
而是每双眼睛独一无二的结构
It's based on the unique crypts,
纹路以及形状
furrows and shapes in the texture.
所以托比亚斯和保罗的虹膜结构可能是一样的
So maybe Tobias and Paul have the same iris pattern.
从统计学角度看是不可能的
Statistically impossible.
第二个关键点
Second data point.
托比亚斯和保罗有着某种联系
Tobias and Paul have some kind of connection.
但测试不是我们做的 所以无从得知
It's not our test,so we don't know.
第三点就是
And the third data point is that
保罗·埃德加·戴瑞 在托比亚斯出生前去世
Paul Edgar Dairy dies before Tobias is born.
正好是怀孕的日子
was conceived.
正好是怀孕的日子 因为托比亚斯
Was conceived,because Tobias is born
2013年七月出生 保罗·埃德加·戴瑞去世于
in July, and Paul Edgar Dairy dies
2012年九月 正好...
in September 2012; that's...
正好十个月 - 我有点听不懂
...that's ten months. - Okay, what are you guys
你们俩说的话了
talking about right now?
你们就像精神错乱了一样
You guys sound like crazy people.
知道吗 这些联系有什么含义吗
Okay? What is this connection referencing?
博士 - 西蒙斯博士
Doctor...- Dr. Simmons.
耶鲁大学的
From Yale.
她给托比亚斯做了这项测试
She did this test on Tobias.
西蒙斯博士？
Dr. Simmons?
耶鲁大学的？
From Yale?
她是能够访问眼部数据库的
She's one of five people who have access
五个人之一 - 什么
to the eye database. - What?
我的公司持有虹膜识别技术的专利
My company owns a patent on iris biometrics
所有眼部扫描的资料都被整合进了一个数据库里
and consolidate all their data into one database.
西蒙斯是有数据库访问权的五人之一
And Simmons is one of five people that have access.
但你也有访问权对吧
But you have access to it, too.
算是吧
Sort of.
我可以找到虹膜数据
I can find the iris code, okay?
查找一个人的资料是否在系统里
Run it and see if it's in the system,
然后查找扫描者的IP地址
and then check the IP address
确认他是何时何地做的眼部扫描
and check when and where it was registered.
这是我能做的
I can do that.
要怎么做
How do you do that?
看这里
Look into that.
好了 另一只眼睛
Okay, other eye.
行了
All right.
虽然看不到你的姓名和个人资料
So I can't get your name or biographicals,
但我可以确认你在这个系统里
but I can see that you are in the system.
好极了 - 是吧
Amazing. - Right?
然后
And that...
你的注册时间地点是
you were registered
2005年 实验室
at the lab in 2005,
我和凯伦应该也是这个时候注册的
and the same should be for Karen and myself.
你怎么想 凯伦
What are you thinking, Karen?
你们听我说
Well, check this out.
保罗和托比亚斯
So Paul and Tobias
假设他们有相同的虹膜结构
have the same iris patterns,let's just say,
并且他们之间存在某种联系
and there's some sort of connection.
那么我们调查的下一步
So the next logical step in our scientific inquiry
就应该是
is to find someone
找到系统中另一对与我们认识的人相同的眼睛
that we do know who's a duplicate in the system.
比如某个已经过世的家人
Like a family member who has died.
就是这样 我们需要另一对案例
That's it. We need another match.
你们知道这从统计学角度来看是不可能的吧
Guys, this is statistically impossible.
什么都不可能找到的
You're not gonna find anything.
你能不能
Can you get a scan
扫描照片上的眼睛
from a photo?
必须是准确对焦的高清照片
It has to be high-res and in focus.
技术上来说是可以的 但是...
Technically,I can do it, but...
我有几百张高清照片
I have hundreds of high-res photos
都是眼部特写 - 好吧
of people's eyes. - All right.
你可以扫描这些
You can scan these.
把硬盘给我
Give me the hard drive.
这太荒唐了
This is ridiculous.
要扫描谁的照片
Who do you want me to run?
先看看我爸的
Hmm, run my father.
托比亚斯·乔治·格雷
Tobias George Gray.
好 - 他两年前过世的
All right.- He died two years ago.
系统里有他的资料
He's in the system, and...
他注册于
and he's registered
希思罗机场 2006年 - 好的
at Heathrow 2006. - Okay.
应该没错
That makes sense.
他经常去伦敦
He was traveling there frequently.
再试试我的叔叔 巴塞尔
Try, um, my Uncle Basil.
他七年前因为癌症去世
He died seven years ago of cancer.
好的
All right.
没有找到
Not found.
试试你的祖父母 - 我的祖父母
Try your grandparents. - My grandparents.
对 - 贝芙和巴里
Yeah. - Bev and Barry.
贝芙
Bev...
她在系统里
She's in the system.
注册于...
Registered...
阿姆斯特丹史基浦机场 1998年
at Schiphol Airport,Amsterdam, in 1998.
数据库里有多少人
How many people are in the database?
大概 几亿人
There's, like, hundreds of millions.
很快就会破十亿了
There's a billion soon.
试试我的祖父母
Try my grandparents.
好的 - 有了
Okay. - Right there.
朱迪在系统里
Judy is in the system.
注册于纽黑文的一家老人院
She was registered in a nursing home in New Haven
2009年 - 马尔科姆呢
in 2009. - And Malcolm?
马尔科姆
Malcolm...
没找到 没有注册
Not found. Not registered.
好了 还有谁吗
All right, so anybody else?
苏菲
Sofi.
好吧 查一下苏菲
Okay, try Sofi.
好
Okay.
苏菲
Sofi.
她在系统里
She's in the system.
应该没错
Yeah, that makes sense.
她可能是在
She was probably scanned
过海关时做的扫描
when she came through Customs.
不 数据显示...
No. It says that...
IP地址的坐标显示 她是在...
the IP address coordinates say that she was scanned
印度德里的一个社区中心做的扫描
in a community center in Delhi, India.
她肯定去过那里
She must have traveled there.
三个月前？
Three months ago?
这不可能
That doesn't make any sense.
肯定是弄错了
That's not right.
一定是系统错误
It's an error.
我们才试到第七个人
It's only the seventh one we tried.
我要出去透透气
I need to get some air.
这到底是怎么回事
What the fuck is happening?
宝宝睡着了吗
Did you put him to bed?
嗯
Yeah.
你该去印度看看
You should go to India.
我不能去印度
I can't go to India.
是不能还是不想
Can't or won't?
印度可没有爱达荷的博伊西那么近 凯伦
India is not Boise, Idaho, Karen.
但那里有个拥有和苏菲相同虹膜结构的人
There is someone there with Sofi's exact iris pattern.
眼睛和大脑是相通的
The eyes and the brain are connected.
如果不同的人能够拥有
If the cellular structure in the eye
相同的眼部细胞结构
is reoccurring from person to person,
那或许大脑中的某些东西
then maybe something in the brain
也是能够被复制的
carries over as well,
比如某种神经系统上的联系
like a neurological link...
也许眼睛从某种程度上说真的是...
Maybe the eye really is some kind of...
灵魂的窗口
window to the soul.
灵魂？凯伦 灵魂？
Soul, Karen? Soul?
我的妻子居然会说『灵魂』这个词？
Is my wife really using the word "soul"?
就像你相信它真的存在一样？
Like you hold any validity in that?
你想怎么称呼它都可以
Call it whatever you want to call it.
西蒙斯博士测试的是我们的儿子
Dr. Simmons was testing a memory connection
和保罗·埃德加·戴瑞间的记忆联系
between our son and Paul Edgar Dairy.
这不是我们的实验 但你可以去印度寻找答案
And it wasn't our test,but you can go to India,
你可以去找那个和苏菲有着一样眼睛的人
and you can find this person with Sofi's eyes,
然后也做一个相同的测试
and you can do the same.
我不能去那里
I can't go there.
不就是印度吗 你为什么不...
It's just India. Why can't you make...
不是印度 我不能回到那个地方！
Not India. I can't go there!
不能回到那段记忆里！
I can't go back there!
我不能回到那一段人生里！
I can't go back to that part of my life!
我做不到！
I can't do it!
我想做的只有放手
I gotta just let it go.
我知道我的丈夫
The man I married...
不是这样的人 他不会让悲伤
I don't think he would let his own grief,
哪怕是巨大的悲伤
even if it was overwhelming,
去阻止自己探索一个
get in the way of what could potentially be
可能是全世界迄今为止
the greatest scientific discovery
最伟大的科学发现
the world has ever seen.
这比你更重要
This is bigger than you.
比我更重要
It's bigger than me.
比苏菲更重要
It's bigger than Sofi.
你应该自己去
Then maybe you should go.
我想去
I would...
但我不了解苏菲
but I didn't know Sofi.
这个结果只是巧合罢了 你明白吧
It's a false positive,you understand?
一定是出错了 一定是的
It's an error;it has to be an error.
从统计学来说这不可能
It's a statistically impossible data point.
如果我让这把手机掉落一千次
If I drop this phone a thousand times,
一百万次
a million times,
有那么一次 它没有下坠
and one time it doesn't fall,
就一次
just once,
它飘了起来
it hovers...
悬在了空中
in the air...
哪怕这是个错误 也是值得探究的错误
...that is an error that's worth looking at.
你真是个固执的人
You're so fucking stubborn.
米拉·戴维的生活
Technology has barely touched
几乎没有享受过科技的福祉
Mira Devi's daily life.
在她的小棚屋里
In her hut, muscle,
日常家务都由双手而非机器完成
not machines,gets the chores done.
但米拉以及数百万相同处境的妇女
That is about to change for Mira
即将迎来生活的转变
and perhaps millions like her.
在服务中心
At this center,
凭借生物识别技术
her irises are scanned
她的虹膜被扫描登记
with biometric devices.
资料随后被上载
They're uploaded and then sent
传送到大型服务器内
to a massive server.
当资料处理完成后
Once this information is processed,
她将获得属于自己 独一无二的12位编码
out comes a 12-digit number for her and her only.
印度独特的身份识别计划
India's unique identification program
于一年前开始实施
started just a year ago.
一旦成功完成
If it succeeds,
印度将成为世界上
India will become the first country in the world
首个在全国范围内实行
using biometric data for identity purposes
生物身份识别技术的国家
on a national scale.
第一次来印度？
First time to India?
是的
It is, actually.
没错
Yeah.
我叫达里尔·麦肯锡
Darryl Mackenzie.
我是伊恩·格雷博士
Uh, Dr. Ian Gray.
是个博士呢
Oh, "Doctor."
两个做着杰出工作的人
Two men, both doing good work.
你是做什么的
What do you do?
我是个商人 不过...
Well, I'm in sales,but, uh...
我也为『那个人』服务
...also do The Man's work.
我是牧师
The Lord's work.
我明白
Uh, of course.
晚安 格雷博士
Good night, Dr. Gray.
你也晚安
Uh, have a good night.
希望我们会再见
Hope our paths cross again.
你好
Hello.
有什么事吗
Uh, can I help you?
你看着像这里的负责人
You seem like the boss of this place.
负责人？我更像是管马戏团的吧
Boss? No, circus manager, more like it.
我叫普莉娅·瓦尔玛
I'm Priya Varma.
请问有什么事
How can I help you?
我是伊恩·格雷博士
I'm Dr. Ian Gray.
我是从美国来的
I'm visiting from America.
我有个请求 听着可能很奇怪
I have a very strange request.
请说
Yes?
我在找一个人
I'm looking for someone
他前不久在这里做的扫描
who was scanned here a while back.
但我不知道他的名字
The thing is, I don't have their name.
只有他眼睛的照片
All I have is a picture of their eyes.
他的眼睛是这样的
This is what their eyes look like.
可能颜色会有点差异
They may not be this exact color.
你为什么要找她
Why are you looking for her?
她遇到什么麻烦了吗
Is she in some kind of trouble?
是个女孩？
Her?
不 当然不是
Uh, no, of course not.
她没有遇到什么麻烦
She's not in trouble.
她的眼睛很特别
She's incredibly special.
你认出她的眼睛来了？
So you do recognize them?
是的 如果我没认错的话
I do, if it is who I think it is,
你为什么要找她
but why are you looking for her?
你看这张照片
Here's another photo.
这是怎么回事
Okay, um,this doesn't make sense.
这是她的眼睛没错
These are her eyes,
但这不是她的脸
but this isn't her face around them.
这就是我要找她的原因
That's exactly why I'm looking for her.
她叫萨罗米娜
Salomina.
萨罗米娜 - 是的
- Salomina? - Yeah.
很可爱的女孩 很聪明
Sweet girl, uh,very smart girl.
但是我有段时间没看见她了
But, uh,I haven't seen her recently.
你最后一次看见她是什么时候
When was the last time you saw her?
几个月前
Uh, a few months ago.
你能帮我找到她吗
Could you help me find her?
我可以给社区中心捐一笔钱
I could make a donation to the community center.
我是说 我打算给社区中心
I mean,I'm going to make a donation
捐一笔钱
to the community center.
我不想说得好像我要收买你一样
I don't want to sound crass,like I'm bribing you,
不过从某种程度上说我是想收买你
but I am kind of bribing you.
不不不 没关系
No, no, no, of course.
我是说 任何捐助都会对社区有很大的帮助
I mean, of course, any donation would help the center.
这件事很重要
It's very important.
求你了
Please.
好吧
Okay.
你明天中午12点
You meet me tomorrow at 12:00
到奥卡拉集市等我 可以吗
at the Okhla market, okay?
好吧 我来帮你们...
All right, I'll take a...
你们想让我拍张照吗
You want me to take a photo of you?
想看吗
You want to see?
看到没 好的
You see? Okay.
你好
Hello.
我本来不想来的
I almost didn't come.
我也担心你不会出现
Yeah, I was worried.
是什么让你改变了心意
What changed your mind?
我...
I, um...
我查了你的背景资料
I did some research on you.
来吧
Come.
你好
Hello.
这些孩子...
Do all these children...
最后都会到社区中心生活吗 还是...
do they eventually end up at the community center or...
一部分会
Some do,
但单单这附近三十个街区
but there are over one million people
就住着一百万多人
living in this 30-block radius alone.
根据登记的资料
According to the registrar,
萨罗米娜和她父母住在这里
Salomina and her parents live here.
我去问问那位女士
I'm gonna ask this lady here.
好的
Okay.
怎么了
What's wrong?
她说什么
What'd she say?
她现在可能像条流浪狗一样生活
She could be living like a stray dog.
她孤身一人
She's totally alone.
她母亲死了 她父亲也死了
Her mother's dead; her father's dead.
她知道社区中心的地址
She knows the address of the community center,
但普莉娅说她已经几周没去过那里了
but Priya said she hasn't been there in weeks.
单是方圆十个街区就有一百万人口
There's a million people living in a ten-block radius.
要找到她几乎是不可能的事
It's gonna be impossible to find her.
你不能现在放弃
Well, you shouldn't give up.
你飞过了半个地球的距离
You flew halfway around the world.
你该继续找下去
You should keep looking.
至少在那里多待几天
At least give it a few days.
我要睡了
I'm gonna go to bed.
晚安
Good night.
再见
Bye.
我到底来这里做什么
What am I doing here?
你疯了
You're mad.
这相当于一枚信号弹
It's a smoke signal.
某个认识她的人会看见的
Someone she knows will see it.
感谢你没把我的号码写在上面
I'm glad you didn't put my number up there.
你好
Hello?
是的
Hi, yes
我侄女的眼睛和那板上印的一样 写着现金奖励的那个
Yeah, my niece has eyes like the picture board, cash reward.
和图片上一样吗
Are they just like the ones in the picture?
我想是的
Yes, I think so.
完全一样吗
Like, exactly?
几乎一样
Uh, very much so.
你侄女几岁了
How old is your niece?
18岁
Eighteen.
我的小侄女15岁
My other niece is 15.
那不是的 抱歉
Oh, no, um, sorry.
谢谢 不是的
Thank you, no.
抱歉 不是我找的人
Sorry, wrong person.
再见
Bye.
你好
Hello?
你会说英语吗
Do you speak English?
我会
Yes, I do.
不好意思 你刚才说什么
I'm sorry, what-what were you saying?
我的眼睛和你登广告寻找的一样
I have the eyes you took up the advertisement for.
你多大了
How old are you?
24岁
Twenty-four.
抱歉
No, sorry.
我要找的是一个小女孩
The person I'm looking for is much younger.
谢谢你打电话过来
No, thank you for calling.
抱歉
Sorry.
真棒
Very good!
我是最棒的 - 我是最棒的吗
I'm the best! - I'm the very best?
我是最棒的
I'm the very best.
棒极了
Very good.
格雷博士 你信教么
Dr. Gray, are you religious?
我信教吗
Am I religious?
你不是调查过我吗
I thought you researched me.
我不信教
I'm not religious.
为什么
Why not?
宗教的基础 是人类于数千年前
Religion is based on scripture written by men
写下的经文
thousands of years ago.
那些观点不容改变也不容置疑
Those beliefs can't be changed or challenged.
是一成不变的
They're fixed.
而在科学中
In science,
伟大的思想家 也在很久以前
great thinkers have written things
写下了各种理论
very long ago,
但那些理论会不断为后来人所修正
but every generation improves upon them.
那些文字不是神圣的
The words are not holy.
爱因斯坦是个伟人 但他并非我们的神
Einstein is a brilliant man,but he's not our god.
他是知识体系进化过程中的一步
He's one step in the evolution of knowledge,
但我们还会继续向前跨越
but we always continue to step forward.
你知道吗
You know...
曾经有位科学家问达赖喇嘛
a scientist once asked the Dalai Lama,
『如果某天科学将你的信仰证伪』
"What would you do if something scientific
『你会怎么做？』
disproved your religious beliefs?"
他在思考良久后回答
And he said, after much thought,
『我会把所有的文章读上一遍』
"I would look at all the papers.
『我会翻看所有的研究结果』
"I'd take a look at all the research
『并试着去理解里面的东西』
"and really try tounderstand things.
『到最后 如果结论清楚地表明』
"And in the end, if it was clear
『科学证据推翻了我的宗教信条』
"that the scientific evidence disproved my spiritual beliefs,
『那我会重新选择我的信仰』
I would change my beliefs."
这回答很好
That's a good answer.
伊恩
Ian...
如果你的科学思想被某些宗教理念证伪
...what would you do if something spiritual
你又会怎么做呢
disproved your scientific beliefs?
亲爱的
Hello, love.
今天银行打电话来
The bank called today.
他们说有每天都有一笔2000美元的转账
They said that $2,000 a day
流向一家印度广告公司
is going to some sketchy Planet India company.
已经累计有两万块了
It's, like, 20k already.
怎么回事
What's going on?
我立了块广告牌
I put up a billboard.
我知道这听着有点极端
I know it sounds a bit extreme,
但这是我唯一能想到的办法了
but it's all I could think of.
伊恩 已经过去几周了
Ian, it's been weeks.
我觉得你还是回来吧
I think you should come back.
凯伦 你之前不是说过
Karen, what happened
寻找后一无所获也算一种发现吗
to turning over rocks and finding nothing is progress?
我觉得这个研究的前景不是很乐观
I'm down with the big picture of all this.
虽然当初是我让你去的
I'm the one who wanted you to go.
但我们也做过不少失败的实验不是吗
But failed experiments are not unknown to us, right?
你可以先回来
We regroup.
我们去找更多别的案例
We look for more matches.
然后再继续尝试
We try again.
回家吧
Please come home.
你会说英语吗
Do you speak English?
一点点
A little.
一点点？
A little?
嗯
Yes.
你叫什么名字
What's your name?
萨罗米娜
Salomina.
Salomina?
嗯
Yes.
萨罗米娜
Salomina,
我是伊恩
I'm Ian.
我的名字是伊恩
My name is Ian.
你肚子饿吗
Are you hungry?
嗯
Yes.
你饿了？ - 嗯
You are? - Yes.
来吧
Come on.
我带你去吃东西
Let's get you some food.
来吧
Come on.
普莉娅 我找到她了
Priya, I found her.
你在哪里 - 我在回酒店的路上
Where are you? - I'm going to the hotel.
你来酒店找我吧
Can you meet me there?
好的 我马上过去
Listen, I'll be right there, okay?
你最喜欢吃什么
What's your favorite food?
草莓
Strawberry.
草莓 草莓就可以了吗？
Strawberry? Just strawberry?
你最喜欢什么颜色
What's your favorite color?
粉色 紫色 蓝色 和绿色
Pink, purple, blue and green.
粉色 紫色 蓝色 和绿色？ - 蓝色和绿色
Pink, purple,blue and green? - Blue and green.
好多啊
That's so many.
看到我的手指了吗 眼睛看着它
See my finger? Can you follow it?
很好
Very good.
很好 很好
Very good. Very good.
很好
Very good.
感觉怎么样 不会难受吧
You okay? You comfortable?
你还好吗  - 嗯
You okay? - Yes.
你在家吗 - 对
Are you there? - Yeah.
让你看个东西 你保证会大吃一惊
I want to show you something that will take your breath away.
凯伦 她叫萨罗米娜
Karen, this is Salomina.
萨罗米娜 这位是凯伦
Salomina, this is Karen.
我需要我的实验助手
I need my lab partner.
好 知道了
Okay. Yeah.
准备就绪
I'm ready.
萨罗米娜 我们来做个简单的游戏
Okay, so, Salomina,it's a very easy game.
我会一次给你看三件东西 然后
I'm going to show you three things, and you pick
你选择最喜欢的一件
the one that's your favorite.
好 - 听明白了吗
- Okay. - You understand?
嗯 - 好的
Yes. - Okay.
开始实验 编号一
Commencing experiment one.
测试相同虹膜结构者
Memory connection between subjects
之间的记忆联系
with identical iris patterns.
明白
Got it.
测试对象 萨罗米娜
Subject,Salomina.
S是 - 关上正门的S
"S" as in... - Shut the front door.
A是 - 神奇的A
"A" as in... - Amazing.
L是 - 爱你的L
"L" as in... - Love you.
O是 - 开明的O
- "O"... - Open-minded.
M是
"M" as in...
大师的M
Maestro.
I是
"I" as in...
伊恩·格雷的I
Ian Gray.
N是
"N" as in...
不可能的N
No way this is true.
A是
"A" as in...
来生的A
Afterlife.
好的 开始吧
Okay. Let's start.
准备好了吗 - 嗯
You ready? - Yes.
好的
Yes? Okay.
开始了
Here we go.
A组 正确
Alpha, correct.
B组 正确
Beta, correct.
C组
Charlie...
正确
...correct.
D组
Delta,
不正确 但不具代表性
incorrect, but it's not a good one.
E组 不正确
Echo, incorrect.
算是吧
Sort of.
好
Okay.
F组 不正确
Foxtrot, incorrect.
G组 不正确
Gamma, incorrect.
H组 不正确
Howie, incorrect.
I组
India...
正确
correct.
J组 不正确
Joker, incorrect.
K组 不正确
Kimo, incorrect.
L组
Love...
正确
correct.
不正确
Incorrect.
U组 正确
Universe, correct.
V组 不正确
Vito, incorrect.
W组 不正确
Wendy, incorrect.
X组 不正确
X-ray, incorrect.
Y组
Yoga...
正确
...correct.
好了
Okay.
得点多少
What's the tally?
44%
44 percent.
勉强高于随机
Which is, um,a touch above random
但这只是边际标准
by an unfortunately standard margin.
你感觉呢
How do you feel?
我相信数字
I think numbers don't lie.
我不是问你的想法 我是问你的感觉
I didn't ask what you think;I asked what you feel.
我感觉
I feel...
自己有点蠢
kind of foolish.
我会尽快回去的
I'll see you soon.
好
Okay.
我做得不好吗
I make bad test?
什么
What?
我做得不好吗
I make bad test?
没有
No.
没有 你做得很好
No, you did fine.
你做得棒极了
You did perfect.
是这个测试太蠢了
It's just a stupid test.
数据库里的图像更新状况如何
Give me an update on the archivist images.
我们已经收集了数百张
We've collected hundreds of images
清晰度足够的图片
at high enough resolution.
只等待您同意扫描了
Just, uh, waiting on your approval to scan.
现在就开始吧
No time like the present.